In black and white
a crack of light blooms
into abstract patterns that
ripple overhead in waves.
A large clot of light bleeds away
forming words ...
"DOCTOR WHO".
The words recede into the
maelstrom of rippling light.
[FAST] More words appear:
The Powerful Enemy.
Written by David Whittaker.
[FAST-ish] The TARDIS, a London Police Box with a flashing beacon, materialises underground in a gloomy cave.
On an alien planet, in a valley between two mountains, rest the remains of long space rocket, hull buckled where it has broken midsection. An external comms dish is still active, scanning the environment as it spins.
The control room of the crashed ship.
The walls are curved, corrugated metal, lined with lockers and equipment.
Above the controls, a light on the scanner flashes.
An attractive young woman with shoulder length fair hair and a dark tunic rushes in from the open crew-entry door leading outside.
She opens a cabin door into another part of the ship.
Vicki looks crestfallen. She nods and walks away.
Vicki looks frightened. Bennett, confined to his bunk, turns on his side, his expression troubled.
Vicki returns to the control room. She sits and lifts a hand mic from the console, and operates the controls.
Vicki stares at the flashing indicator.
Inside the console room of the TARDIS, the Doctor is sleeping in a chair. Ian and Barbara examine the console.
The Doctor yawns.
He operates the scanner control.
Ian and Barbara look at each other in the awkward silence as the Doctor remembers Susan is gone.
Barbara operates the control and the doors open.
Barbara, Ian and the Doctor step out of the Police Box and into a cave, lit intermittently by the TARDIS beacon.
He steps back into the TARDIS.
They duck through a passageway in the cave.
A strange creature watches them go.
It is tall and reptilian, wearing a long, black robe.
It has a collar of fins like palm-fronds. Its eyes are on stalks, and its face resembles the mouthparts of an insect, each mandible ending in a sharp tusk.
It touches the TARDIS with a scaley claw.
Ian and Barbara step out of the cave onto a ledge of roughly textured rock, high on a mountain.
They look out across the landscape.
He grasps her hand.
The spiny reptilian creature from the cave advances on them.
Barbara squeezes his hand in warning.
Ian ducks into the cave.
The creature then blocks the entrance and advances on Barbara.
She tries to move past, but the creature grabs her.
They struggle, and she falls backwards off the ledge.
In the TARDIS the Doctor examines the stone with a magnifying glass.
He consults his handwritten notes.
On the ledge, the creature approaches the cave entrance and brandishes a stubby, ornamental sceptre with a clawed head.
It points the sceptre at the cave, holding it upright in outstretched talons.
The powerful energy causes an explosion. Rocks fall from the cave roof and block the entrance.
Ian is clipped by a flying rock and collapses near the TARDIS.
Dust fills the air.
The TARDIS doors fling open.
At the foot of the mountain, Barbara lies unconscious on the sand, clutching a broken tree branch.
A shadow falls over her.
The cave.
In the control room of the rocket, Vicki busies herself making up a bunk.
She glances out the window and, with guilty haste, snatches a handful of glittering stones from a locker and sits at a table, pretending to scrutinise them.
The entry door slides open and the tall, insect-headed creature in the black robe stalks in.
Vicki looks terrified. She nods mutely.
He brandishes the sceptre menacingly at the trembling Vicki.
He turns and opens the cabin door.
Vicki presses her ear against the door, listening.
The creature navigates the wreckage in the passage and pushes the door to the cabin.
The creature, Koquillion, pushes the door open.
Vicki rushes back to the bunk, and flings back the covers to reveal Barbara!
She turns, sobbing to Barbara, who awkwardly comforts her.
Vicki, distraught, turns away, wiping her eyes.
She rubs her eyes and nose.
Barbara looks grim.
The cave. Ian and the Doctor explore with a large battery-powered torch.
In the rocket ship.
Vicki fetches a gun from a locker.
Frightened, Vicki bundles Barbara back under the covers, and sits at the mess table.
Bennett leans on the door.
Vicki flings back the covers,  and Barbara crawls out from under them.
Bennett looks troubled.
In the cave, Ian and the Doctor, backs against the wall, sidle along a narrow rocky ledge.
The Doctor stumbles, but Ian stops him falling.
Ian aims the torch down into the drop.
On the rocky floor below, a segmented, grub-like creature stirs.
It is alligator sized, with rows of sharp teeth and shining eyes on stalks.
There are metal rings set into the rock.
The rings are embedded in the mouth of embossed monsters decorating the wall. They swing themselves to safety.
Spikes shoot out of the wall either side of Ian.
The Doctor wrestles with the mechanism.
Below, the grub-creature looks up expectantly.
More spikes emerge.
Words appear: Next Episode - Desperate Measures.
That episode featured William Hartnell,
William Russell, Jacqueline Hill, Maureen O'Brien
and Ray Barrett.
The incidental Music was by Tristam Carey;
Title Music: Ron Grainer and the BBC Radiophonic Workshop;
Producer: Verity Lambert;
Director: Christopher Barry.
Copyright BBC 1965.
Independent Audio Description Script by Brett Coulstock.